Mockingbirds are badass.
الطيور المحاكية غريبة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They are.
إنها.
Mockingbirds -- that's Mimus polyglottos --
الطيور المحاكية-- التي تحاكي--
are the emcees of the animal kingdom.
هم نجوم مملكة الحيوان.
They listen and mimic and remix what they like.
إنهم يستمعون ويقلدون ويصيغون ما يريدون.
They rock the mic outside my window every morning.
إنهم يصدعون المايكروفون خارج نافذتي كل صباح.
I can hear them sing the sounds of the car alarms
أستطيع سماعهم يصدرون أصوات جرس إنذار سيارتي
like they were songs of spring.
كأنها أصوات الربيع.
I mean, if you can talk it, a mockingbird can squawk it.
أعني، إن كنت ستقولها، الطائر المحاكي يمكنه أن يصرخ بها.
So check it, I'm gonna to catch mockingbirds.
لذا تأكدوا، سأقوم بصيد طيور محاكية.
I'm going to trap mockingbirds all across the nation
سأقوم بنصب شرك لكل الطيور المحاكية عبر البلاد
and put them gently into mason jars like mockingbird Molotov cocktails.
وأضعهم برفق داخل جرارات ماسون مثل كوكتيل مولوتوف للطيور المحاكية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. And as I drive through a neighborhood,
نعم. وبينما أقود في الجور،
say, where people got-a-lotta, I'll take a mockingbird I caught
لنقل، حيث الكثير من الناس، سأخذ الطير المحاكي الذي قبضته
in a neighborhood where folks ain't got nada and just let it go, you know.
في الجوار حيث لا يعلم الناس وسأطلق سراحه.
Up goes the bird, out come the words, "Juanito, Juanito,
تطير عالياً، وتأتي الكلمات، " جوني، جوني،
vente a comer mi hijo!"
تعال لتأكل يا بني!"
Oh, I'm going to be the Johnny Appleseed of sound.
أوه، سأرى جوني سعيد بهذا الصوت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Cruising random city streets, rocking a drop-top Cadillac
تجوب شوارع مدينة عشوائية، مزعجة سيارة كاديلاك بلا سقف
with a big backseat, packing like 13 brown paper Walmart bags
مع مقعد خلفي كبير، عليه 13 شنطة بُنية اللون من وول مارت
full of loaded mockingbirds, and I'll get everybody.
مليئة بالطيور المحاكية، وسأعرف كل شئ عن الجميع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll get the nitwit on the network news saying,
سأشاهد فاصل الأخبار يقول،
"We'll be back in a moment with more on the crisis."
" سنعود خلال لحظات مع المزيد من الأزمات."
I'll get some asshole at a watering hole asking what brand the ice is.
سأعرف بعض الأوغاد في حُفر الماء يسألون ما نوع الثلج.
I'll get that lady at the laundromat who always seems to know what being nice is.
سأعرف تلك المرأة في المغسلة التي تعرف دائماً كيف تبدو جميلة.
I'll get your postman making dinner plans.
سأعرف ساعي بريدك يخطط للعشاء.
I'll get the last time you lied.
سأعرف آخر مرة كذبت فيها أنت.
I'll get, "Baby, just give me the frickin' TV guide."
سأعرف،" حبيبتي، رجاء ناوليني دليل التفاز الغريب."
I'll get a lonely, little sentence with real error in it,
سأعرف جملة صغيرة وحيدة مع خطأ حقيقي
"Yeah, I guess I could come inside, but only for a minute."
"نعم، أعتقد أن بمستطاعي الدخول، لكن لدقيقة واحدة فقط."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll get an ESL class in Chinatown learning "It's Raining, It's Pouring."
سأحضر درس لغة إنجليزي في المدينة الصينية يتعلمون، إنها تمطر، إنها تصب."
I'll put a mockingbird on a late-night train just to get an old man snoring.
سأضع طير محاكي في قطار منتصف الليل لأسمع رجل مسن يشخر.
I'll get your ex-lover telling someone else, "Good morning."
سأعرف حبيبك السابق يخبر شخصاً آخر، " صباح الخير."
I'll get everyone's good mornings.
سأعرف الجميع يقولون صباح الخير
I don't care how you make 'em.
لا أهتم كيف تقولوها.
Aloha. Konichiwa. Shalom. Ah-Salam Alaikum.
ألوها. كونيتشوا. شالوم. السلام عليكم.
Everybody means everybody, means everybody here.
الجميع يعني الجميع، أعني كل شخص هنا.
And so maybe I'll build a gilded cage.
وربما أبني قفص ذهبي.
I'll line the bottom with old notebook pages.
وسأخطط أسفله بصفحات مذكرات قديمة.
Inside it, I will place a mockingbird for --
داخله، سأضع طائر محاكي ل --
short explanation, hippie parents.
شرح قصير، آباء الهيبي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What does a violin have to do with technology?
ما علاقة الكمان بالتكنلوجيا؟
Where in the world is this world heading?
إلى اين يتجه هذا العالم؟
On one end, gold bars --
في جانب، قبضان الذهب --
on the other, an entire planet.
وعلى جانب آخر، كل الكوكب.
We are 12 billion light years from the edge.
نحن على بُعد 12 مليار سنة ضوئية من النهاية.
That's a guess.
ذلك تخميني.
Space is length and breadth continued indefinitely,
الفضاء هو طول وعرض يتواصل بلا نهاية،
but you cannot buy a ticket to travel commercially to space in America
لكنك لا تستطيع شراء تذكرة لتجوب الفضاء تجارياً في أمريكا
because countries are beginning to eat like us, live like us and die like us.
لأن البلدان أصبحت تأكل مثلنا، تعيش مثلنا وتموت مثلنا.
You might wanna avert your gaze, because that
قد ترغب في تجنب النظر، لأن ذلك
is a newt about to regenerate its limb,
نيوت قارب على إعادة تجديد أطرافه،
and shaking hands spreads more germs than kissing.
ويصافح بنشر المزيد من الجراثيم التي تقبّل.
There's about 10 million phage per job.
هناك 10 ملايين فج لكل وظيفة.
It's a very strange world inside a nanotube.
إنه عالم غريب داخل أنبوب بحجم النانو.
Women can talk; black men ski; white men build strong buildings;
تستطيع النساء الكلام، والسود يتزلجوا، يبني البيض مباني قوية،
we build strong suns.
نحن نبني شمساً خارقة.
The surface of the Earth is absolutely riddled with holes,
سطح الأرض بالطبع ملئ بالحفر،
and here we are, right in the middle.
ونحن ها هنا، تماماً في المنتصف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is the voice of life that calls us to come and learn.
إنه صوت الحياة الذي ينادينا لنأتي ونتعلم.
When all the little mockingbirds fly away,
عندما تطير كل الطيور المحاكية بعيداً،
they're going to sound like the last four days.
سيصدروا صوتاً مثل الأربع أيام الأخيرة.
I will get uptown gurus, downtown teachers,
سأعرف علماء المدينة، معلمي المدينة،
broke-ass artists and dealers, and Filipino preachers, leaf blowers,
الفنانين المبدعين والتجار، وحارقي الورق، الدعاة الفليبنيين،
bartenders, boob-job doctors, hooligans, garbage men,
السقاة، الأطباء المعتوهين، مثيري الشغب ورجال القمامة،
your local Congressmen in the spotlight, guys in the overhead helicopters.
ممثلك في البرلمان تحت الضوء، الرجال في مقدمة الهلوكوبتر.
Everybody gets heard.
الجميع مسمُعون.
Everybody gets this one, honest mockingbird as a witness.
الجميع سيحصل على واحدة، طائر محاكي صادق كشهاد.
And I'm on this.
وسوف أعمل على هذا على هذا.
I'm on this 'til the whole thing spreads,
سوف أعمل على هذا حتى ينتشر كل شئ،
with chat rooms and copycats and moms maybe tucking kids into bed
مع غرفة الدردشة والمقلدين والأمهات ربما يضعون الأطفال على الفراش
singing, "Hush, little baby, don't say a word.
يغنون، أسكت طفلي الصغير، لا تقل كلمة،
Wait for the man with the mockingbird."
أنتظر الرجل مع الطائر المحاكي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. And then come the news crews, and
نعم. ثم يأتي طاقم الأخبار، و
the man-in-the-street interviews, and the letters to the editor.
ولقاءات الرجل في الشارع، الخطابات والمحرر.
Everybody asking, just who is responsible for this citywide,
يسأل الجميع ، من المسئول من هذه المدينة،
nationwide mockingbird cacophony, and somebody finally is going to tip
نشاز الطائر المحاكي في كل البلاد وأخيراً شخص ما سيقوم باخطار
the City Council of Monterey, California off to me,
مجلس مدينة مونتري، كالفورنيا عني،
and they'll offer me a key to the city.
وسيعرضون عليّ مفتاح للمدينة.
A gold-plated, oversized key to the city
مفتاح ثقيل للمدينة بقلادة ذهبية
and that is all I need, 'cause if I get that, I can unlock the air.
وذلك كل ما أريد، لأني إذا حصلت عليه، ساقوم بتحرير الهواء.
I'll listen for what's missing, and I'll put it there.
سأستمع لكل شئ ناقص، وأقوم بإكماله هناك.
Thank you, TED.
شكراً لكم، تيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Wow.
كريس أندرسون: واو.
Wow.
واو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)